<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King and Queen in Their Majesties chappel at St. James's, on the twentieth Sunday after Pentecost, Octob. 25. 1685 by the Reverend Father John Persall ...</title>
            <author>Persall, John, 1633-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11063</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12199335</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12199335</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56078</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56078)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 872:52)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King and Queen in Their Majesties chappel at St. James's, on the twentieth Sunday after Pentecost, Octob. 25. 1685 by the Reverend Father John Persall ...</title>
                  <author>Persall, John, 1633-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56078:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56078:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the King and Queen, IN Their MAJESTIES
Chappel at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, on the Twentieth <hi>Sunday</hi> after
<hi>Pentecoſt, Octob.</hi> 25. 1685.</p>
            <p>By the Reverend Father <hi>JOHN PERSALL,</hi> Of the Society of
JESUS, Profeſſor of Divinity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the
King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, for his Houſhold and Chappel. 1686.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:56078:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56078:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before THEIR MAJESTIES, On the Twentieth
<hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Pentecoſt, Octob.</hi> 25. 1685.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Erat quidam Regulus, cujus filius infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabatur.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joannis c.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 48.</bibl>
                  <p>There was a certain Nobleman, whoſe ſon was ſick.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Holy Church, in this Days Goſpel, invites us all to the
Bed-ſide of a Rich, Noble, Young, but Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prince, who lies groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at
Deaths-door, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56078:3"/>his Plenty of other
things, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Beggar for a little Breath, which all the Power of the
World is not able to afford him. I wiſh, that the Followers of Senſuality,
who make Pleaſure their God, live as if they were never to die, imagine Time
to ſtand, and laugh at Diſcourſes of another World, as Fables only for
the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment and Paſtime of this: I wiſh (I ſay) they would turn
their Thoughts hither a little while, and behold the diſmal Theatre, whereon
every one of them muſt one day infallibly act the ſame Part, which now this
Noble Youth repreſents before them; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling betwixt two great Eternities,
of Happineſs above, and Miſery below, and uncertain which of the two is to
be their Lot. Now, tho' we go no further, certainly the Pangs of a dying
Prince, and Death triumphing over Wealth, Nobility, and Youth, is an Emblem,
clear enough, of the Vanity and Uncertainty of Worldly Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56078:3"/>and might well deſerve to be the Subject of our preſent
Conſideration.<note place="margin">Serm. 44. de Verbis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> But
becauſe I hear the Great St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin (ſpeaking of our Saviour's
reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Widows Son to Life)</hi> adviſe us, That it was our LORD's
Intention, that, by what he acted viſibly towards the Body, we ſhould
underſtand his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Operations on the Soul, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his
exteriour and Corporal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, to an interiour and Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Senſe:
<hi>Dominus noſter JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S ea, quae faciebat corporalitèr,
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualitèr volebat intelligi.</hi> It ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be my
preſent Endeavour, Firſt, by the Sickneſs of this Youth, to lay before
your Eyes the Sickneſs of a Soul in Sin; and, Secondly, from the
Circumſtances of his Cure, we'l gather the Means for the Curing of our Souls.
But becauſe I am too conſcious of my own Weakneſs, to hope for any Fruit
from my Words, unleſs the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt vouchſafe to put them in my Mouth,
and ſpeak them again to the <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56078:4"/>Hearts of my Hearers, I muſt
have recourſe to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> whoſe powerful
Interceſſion is an Aquaeduct or Channel (as the devout St.
<hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> aſſures us) through which Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Gifts are conveyed
unto us. Wherefore let us humbly invoke the ſame, ſaluting her with the
Angel, <hi>Ave Maria, &amp;c.</hi>
               <q>Erat quidam Regulus, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>IT being then my intent by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Sickneſs of the Body
to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the inviſible Sickneſs of the Soul, let us enter a little
into the Chamber of this Dying Prince, which probably you will find adorn'd
with the richeſt Tapeſtry, beautify'd with choice Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and ſet out
with other Moveables of the higheſt Price: The Curtains, Vallence, and Canopy
of the Bed, all proportionable to the Nobility and Greatneſs of their
Maſter; but approach a little towards that ſtately Bed, draw
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56078:4"/>open thoſe Royal Curtains, and ſee what lies within: A
gaſping Life, an half-living Death, a breathing Carcaſs! His ſinking Eyes
already ſeek their Grave: his pale and wan Countenance puts us in mind of his
Winding-ſheet: the feeble and unactive Condition of his Body declares, that
he is Death's Cloſe Priſoner: the Panting of his Heart is a ſad warning,
that the fatal Stroke is ready to be given, which muſt break aſunder the
Gordian Tye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Soul and Body. And is this He, on whom ſo much Gallantry
do's at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend? Is it to him, thoſe Hangings, Cabinets, and Embroider'd
Curtains do belong? This certainly is the Fable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and not a Pearl on a
Dunghil, but a Dunghil in the midſt of Pearls.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the viſible Effects and Conſequences of this
Prince's Corporal Sickneſs: Let us now try, how far they will lead us towards
the Diſcovery of the inviſible Effects of a Spiritual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56078:5"/>If you view the Chamber or Bed, wherein a dying Soul lies
gaſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what for the moſt part more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious? It is one perhaps of
theſe trimm'd-up Beauties of the World, which ſeem to out-ſhine the Suns
brighteſt Beams. Gold, Silver, Pearls, and whatſoever the blind World calls
Precious, is all too little to ſet them out. But turn hither the Eyes of your
Underſtanding, draw open thoſe gay Curtains by a ſerious Conſideration,
and look on that Soul, which lies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them. <hi>O quale Monſtrum! What a
Monſter!</hi> Had we Eyes of Angels, it would appear far more hideous to us,
than the expiring Carcaſs, which we juſt now beheld. The Poyſon of his
Diſeaſe had dry'd and wither'd up his Body, conſum'd all his Spirits, and
the Soul being now ready to depart, all the Train of Beauteous Features had
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taken their leave. But the Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Sin is yet far ranker, and its
Effects upon a poor infected Soul far <pb n="7" facs="tcp:56078:5"/>more deplorable. It
conſumes to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing all her Subſtance, all the Stock of Grace whereby
ſhe flouriſht. The Sun of Juſtice, her only Life, is ready to withdraw
his Divine Rays, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all the Flowers of Vertue muſt needs dry
up and wither; ſo that ſhe, who before had Beauty enough to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour the
very Fountain of Beauty, is now become the Source of a Poyſon, rank enough to
infect the whole World. She is a meer Sink of Loathſomneſs and Corruption.
What is ſhe elſe, but a putrifying Carcaſs, feeding the Worms of a bad
Conſcience, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendring innumerable venemous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, I mean, the
curſed Brood of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Habits? She breaths forth ſuch a Stench, that were
our Corporeal Senſes capable of being wrought on by Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Objects, it
would not be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for us, to live within the Sphere of its Activity.
For the truth of all this, I appeal to thoſe Saints, to whom Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God
has given a more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56078:6"/>Light, for the diſcovering the
Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and Uglineſs of Sin. St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> calls Sin the only
Evil, aſſerting, <hi>That we ought to abhor nothing but Sin, no not even
Hell it ſelf.</hi> And the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof will appear clearly, if we
conſider the Nature of an Humane Soul. She is created to the perfect Image of
her Creator, and participates in an high Degree of his Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<hi>Divinae Particula Aurae:</hi> Hence ſhe has in her a ſtrong and
forcible Appetite of being united to her God, and conſequently cannot be at
reſt, whilſt ſhe is ſeparated from him; but in this Night of Sin, the
Fogs, ariſing from a corrupted Will, do ſo obſcure the Underſtanding,
that, tho' the Soul perceives an unquiet Appetite within her ſelf of ſome
great Good, yet what that Good is, or where to find it, ſhe knows not, and
falls on that which comes next, Senſual Pleaſures, Riches, Honours,
miſtaking the Rivulets for the Fountains, but ſtill ends with a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56078:6"/>Reſtleſneſs and Diſſatisfaction. So
<hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> after he had glutted himſelf with all the Pleaſures ſo
great a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge could invent, and ſo great a Power could procure,
<hi>Quicquid deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raverunt oculi mei, non negavi eis, quin omni voluptate
fruerentur;</hi> he experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd in all <hi>Vanitatem,</hi> a certain
Empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, <hi>Afflictionem ſpiritus,</hi> an Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mind;
becauſe Nothing is good, or according to the innate Appetite of the Soul, but
GOD; on the other ſide, nothing is ill, or contrary to this innate Appetite,
but Sin. And hence it was, that thoſe <hi>Pauls, Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Hilaries,</hi>
who liv'd on raw Herbs, lay on the hard Ground, ſpent their Days in Prayer
and Mortification, and were depriv'd of all the Delights of Senſe, never
complain'd of Miſery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe having God, and being united to him, they
ſeem'd to want nothing; whereas <hi>Solomon,</hi> tho' abounding with Riches,
being without God, ſeem'd to have nothing. So true it is, that there
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56078:7"/>is nothing ſatisfactory to the Rational Soul, but God; and
nothing hurtful or grievous to it, but Sin. The Holy Archbiſhop of
<hi>Canterbury,</hi> St. <hi>Anſelm,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts, That he would rather
leap into the eternal Flames of Hell <hi>purus a peccato,</hi> free from Sin,
than <hi>peccati labe pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus coelorum regna tenere,</hi> defil'd with Sin to
poſſeſs Heaven. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> has many things to the ſame
purpoſe; but none more emphatically deſcribes this Plague than St.
<hi>Peter Chryſologus. 'Tis the nature of Sin,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to breathe
forth a certain venemous Vapour in the Soul, which ſo dims the two Lights of
Faith and Reaſon, that it leaves her wholly in Darkneſs: So that being led
by Paſſion, ſhe throws her ſelf from one Precipice to another, till
ſhe comes at length to the very Brink of Hell, and yet ſees not all this
while, whither ſhe has faln, or how near ſhe is to her eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ruine.
Beſides this, her Fever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts her with an inſatiable Thirſt of all
thoſe things which increaſe her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56078:7"/>and, on
the contrary ſide,</hi> Fonti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus dulciſſimis amara ſalſedo, <hi>it
ſo ſpoils and vitiates her Taſte, that thoſe Fountains of Graces and
Spiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, the</hi> Sacraments, Sermons, Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Books, <hi>and
the like, which to a Soul in Health are moſt ſavory and delicious, to her
are as bitter as Gall.</hi> To this purpoſe St. <hi>Chryſologus.</hi> By
which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently appears the deplorable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a Soul in Sin, had
we a Senſe or Underſtanding capable of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it. But as the
Sickneſs of the Body is never the leſs dangerous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Patient
perceives not the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of his Diſeaſe: So the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Sick
Soul is never the leſs miſerable, becauſe in this Lethargy of Fleſh and
Blood, ſhe diſcerns not her own Miſery. And now, if nothing elſe will
ſerve the turn, let at leaſt the Danger of an Everlaſting Death move us
to look after a Cure, and that as earneſtly and efficaciouſly, as the thing
deſerves. When a wiſe and <pb n="12" facs="tcp:56078:8"/>skilful Phyſician tells his
Patient, that he is in Danger of Death, it makes him preſently ſeek a
Remedy, attend to the Phyſician's Preſcriptions, and put all diligently in
execution. But what is the Death of the Body, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd with the Death of the
Soul? That is only Temporal; This, Eternal: That implies a Separation of the
Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from a Rational Soul; This, the Separation of the Soul from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
of all Happineſs, Almighty God: That leaves the Body, bereav'd indeed of
Senſe, yet without Pain; This bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the Soul in Hell, there to ſuffer,
and for ever, ſuch Torments, that all the Pains and Torments of this Life are
nothing to them. When I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times conſider with my ſelf, that it may be,
it is not impoſſible, that I ſhould one day groan under the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Burden
of Eternal Damnation, tho' I go no farther, reflecting only on a meer
Poſſibility of ſo great a Miſery, it makes my whole Body tremble: My
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56078:8"/>Hair ſtands an end, my Heart pants, and my Bones are
almoſt disjointed with Fear. But foraſmuch as concerns a Probability
thereof, and ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability too, that the contrary is impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, who
is there that is not dead already, or quite void of Senſe, who can live with
ſuch a Thought, under ſuch an Apprehenſion? And yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that
thoſe who follow their ſenſual Inclinations, and ſcarce ever
ſeriouſly think of their Souls, are in a Probability, and in a very great
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of being damn'd. Damn'd! Oh what a Deluge of Miſery is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
in that little word, <hi>Damn'd!</hi> Let theſe Conſiderations, Beloved
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſink into our Souls; Let a juſt Horrour of Sin ſeiſe
upon our Hearts: And ſo diſpos'd, let us paſs to the Second Part, and
learn to cure our Souls, by weighing the Circumſtances, and conſidering the
Particulars of this young Prince's miraculous Cure.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56078:9"/>
            <p>The Father of our Sick Youth no ſooner heard of our Saviour's
coming that way, but he preſently went unto him. The firſt thing then, we
are to do, is to have recourſe to the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian. <hi>Abiit ad eum,</hi>
ſays the Text, <hi>He departed unto him;</hi> the word <hi>Abiit</hi> here
ſignifying not only a <hi>Going to,</hi> but a <hi>Going from.</hi> Many are
willing enough to go to the Heavenly Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, on condition that they may
not go from the World. They will (I ſay) go to him, but not follow his
Advice, in parting with their Riches, Honour, Pleaſure, the Source and
Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of their peccant Humour, and conſequently the Cauſe of their
Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is to Preſent him with our Petitions: <hi>Et
rogabat eum: And he ask'd him.</hi> Some come to him, but, like the proud
Phariſee, ask him nothing, juſtifying themſelves, and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56078:9"/>to acknowledge their Wants, or any need they have of a
Phyſician. <hi>Quid rogaverit Deum, quaere in verbis ejus, &amp; nihil
invenies: Examine a little</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>the
Phariſee's words, and ſee what he ask'd of God, and you ſhall find, that
he ask'd nothing.</hi> This is not the way: But, on the contrary, we muſt
with Humility own our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and Sickneſs, if ever we expect a Cure. We
muſt <hi>rogare,</hi> beg with an humble Confidence, <hi>ut deſcendat,</hi>
that he will come down to us; at leaſt, that he will be pleas'd to caſt
down an Eye of Mercy upon our ſad and helpleſs Condition; and then we ought
not to doubt of a Remedy from that Hand, which is ſo far from repelling us
when we ask, that its Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Bounty is always beckning to us, and
encouraging us to ask.</p>
            <p>The third thing which we ought to do, is of very great moment, and
that, for want whereof, many have been eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56078:10"/>loſt;
and it is, not only to Go, nor only to Ask, but to do Both in time. 'Tis a
dangerous thing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the Cure of our Souls. Alas! how many are there who
at this inſtant fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly deplore in eternal Torments, that ever they put
off ſo important a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern? We muſt then in this imitate the Father of our
Sick Youth, who was careful in the beginning. <hi>Incipie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat mori; His Son
began to die;</hi> and he was ſollicitous that our Saviour might come, before
he had quite gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up the Ghoſt. <hi>Deſcende, priuſquàm moriatur
Filius meus: Come down</hi> (ſays he) <hi>before my Son dies.</hi> I am not
ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that divers Interpreters, and ſome Holy Fathers alſo, accuſe
theſe Words of want of Faith, as if an Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence could not as eaſily
have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd him Dead to Life, as Sick to Health; yet they muſt all
grant, that 'tis an excellent Prayer for a dying Soul, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, deſcende,
priuſquàm moriatur Anima mea; Lord, vouchſafe to come, before my
Soul dies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56078:10"/>
            <p>Conſider all the Cures, which our Saviour wrought, and you will
ſtill find the appearance of moſt Difficulty, where the Diſeaſe had
made the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Progreſs. <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead, and now four days
in his Grave, and how much is to be done to raiſe him? Firſt, Our Saviour
muſt come in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, tho' his Diſciples diſſuade him from expoſing
himſelf to ſo much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>The Jews,</hi> ſaid they, <hi>did but
juſt now endeavour to ſtone thee, and wilt thou again venture thy ſelf
amongſt them?</hi> He goes notwithſtanding this, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to the
Monument, Firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Grave-ſtone to be remov'd, Then he afflicts
himſelf, <hi>turbavit ſemet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum,</hi> and even weeps, <hi>lacrimatus
eſt JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S:</hi> Then he prays to his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Father; and at laſt
<hi>voce magnâ cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mavit,</hi> he cries out with a loud voice,
<hi>Lazare, veni foras; Lazarus, come forth.</hi> What was all this for? Would
not a <hi>Lazarus vivit, Lazarus lives,</hi> have done <pb n="18" facs="tcp:56078:11"/>the
Buſineſs, tho' our Bleſſed Saviour had been as far diſtant from
<hi>Lazarus,</hi> as he was now from our Sick Prince? It were a Blaſphemy to
affirm the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. But <hi>Lazarus,</hi> Dear Chriſtians, was the Type of
an inveterate and hardned Sinner; and our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour on this
occaſion was not ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to let us ſee the Uncontrollable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of
his Omnipotence, as he was to ſhew us, how much it goes to his Heart, that a
Sinner ſhould delay his Converſion, till he becomes buried in ill Habits,
and is kept under Ground by the weighty Grave-ſtone of his own Obſtinacy;
and withal, how dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult it is, that ſuch an one ſhould be again
reſtor'd to the Life of Grace.</p>
            <p>The Widows Son was not yet bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd, but only carry'd out to
Burial: <hi>Efferebatur filius unicus Matris ſuae.</hi> And conſequently
our Saviour raiſes him with a far leſs appearance of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty: He comes,
but neither afflicts <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56078:11"/>himſelf, nor weeps; he only touches
the Bier, and commands the dead Youth to riſe; <hi>Adoleſcens, tibi dico,
Surge:</hi> and his Commands were preſently obey'd; for the dead Youth
aroſe, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedit, qui erat mortuus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Daughter of the Prince of the Synagogue was but newly dead,
nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buried, nor carry'd out to Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. Our Saviour comes, and without
ſpeaking to her, took her by the Hand, and rais'd her; <hi>Tenuit manum ejus,
&amp; ſurrexit Puella.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our young Prince was not ſo much as dead, but only
<hi>incipiebat mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> he began to die, and ſo deſerv'd the eaſieſt
Cure of all; for our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our neither comes in Perſon, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his
Diſeaſe; but only tells his Father, <hi>Filius tuus vivit, Thy Son is
well,</hi> and at that very hour <hi>reliquit eum Febris, his Fever left
him.</hi> By all which our Saviour would teach us, how wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56078:12"/>he is to hear a Sinners Petition, when it is preſented to
him in time; and how unwillingly he hearkens to thoſe, who put off all to the
laſt Point. Daily Experience teaches us this Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there ſcarce
being a Country which do's not afford us moſt terrible Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of
thoſe, who, delaying from time to time the Amendment of their Lives, have
felt the heavy Hand of God's Judgment, being taken at una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares out of this
Life, and in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they leaſt ſuſpected, ſwallow'd up, and bury'd
in Hell: <hi>Momento deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt in Infernum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, we have a good God, a merciful God, a patient God, who
expects day after day the Converſion of a Sinner; but we muſt know, that a
certain Period is pitch'd upon, and decreed from all Eternity, that will wholly
ſtop the Current of Mercy, and open a way to Juſtice: for tho, as long as
any Sinner lives in this <pb n="21" facs="tcp:56078:12"/>Life with the uſe of Reaſon,
Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God never denies him his ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Grace; yet after ſuch a
determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Period, he either takes him out of this Life, or permits him to
fall into ſuch Blindneſs and Hardneſs of Heart, that he never will
recover, tho' he always may: <hi>Sic enim</hi> (ſays St.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>excaecat, ſic obdurat De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, deſerendo, &amp; non
adjuvando, quod occulto judicio facere poteſt, iniquo non poteſt: God do's
ſo blind and ſo harden a Sinner, by forſaking him, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing his
Help from him, as that his Judgment indeed is ſecret and hidden, but never
unjuſt.</hi> For, <hi>Hoe eorum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem meruiſſe Reſpondeo: I
anſwer</hi> (ſays the ſame Saint) <hi>to thoſe who complain hereof,
That this is what they themſelves</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> by their own perverſe
Will) <hi>have deſerv'd.</hi> Poor <hi>Samuel,</hi> with Eyes and Heart
lifted up to Heaven, pray'd for <hi>Saul;</hi> but it was too late: <hi>Why do
you ask me for him,</hi> (ſays Almighty God) when <hi>abjeci eum,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56078:13"/>I have caſt him off?</hi> Remember the two firſt
Chapters of the Prophet <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> where our Lord ſpeaks thus to ſeven
different Countries, <hi>viz. Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, Gaza, Tyre, Edom, Ammon, Moab,</hi>
and at laſt even to his Elect Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Iſrael: Super
tribus Sceleribus;</hi> for three heinous Crimes, Patience: but <hi>ſuper
quatuor non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertam,</hi> to the fourth no Mercy. Who knows, but this very
Moment may be the laſt Period and Admonition, the laſt Grace which Almighty
God hath decreed for ſome one or more of us here preſent, in ſuch manner,
that, if it be neglected, we ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh irrecoverably for all Eternity?
<hi>Super quatuor non convertam.</hi> No, the Period is come, <hi>Mittam
ignem,</hi> and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now remains, excepting only the dreadful Torments of
an unquencha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fire.</p>
            <p>O let us then, every one of us, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into our own Souls, and
make an <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56078:13"/>exact Scrutiny into their preſent State and
Condition. Let us examine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Terrene and Senſual Pleaſures have not
caſt them into the Peſtilent Fever of a violent Paſſion, ſo that
<hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt mori,</hi> they begin to die, to die (I ſay) to God and
Heaven. If ſo, let us forthwith have recourſe to the Phyſician;
<hi>Abeamus ad eum;</hi> let us go from all other Entertainments and Concerns
unto him: <hi>Rogemus,</hi> let us throw our ſelves at the Sacred Feet of our
Crucified Lord, acknowledge our Miſery, and beg his Aſſiſtance:
<hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, deſcende, priuſquàm moriatur Anima mea; O Lord,
vouchſafe to come down to me, before my Soul be dead.</hi> O my Lord, my God,
who didſt eſteem Sin to be ſo great an Evil, that thou thoughtſt it
worth thy Labour to come down from Heaven to Earth, to ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize and die upon a
Croſs, that thou mightſt free us from it; For what didſt thou open Five
Divine Fountains of thy Sacred Blood, ſave only to cleanſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56078:14"/>us from ſo foul a Stain? Ah! ſhew us now, that <hi>non
eſt abbreviata Manus Domini,</hi> that thy Mercy hath as great a reach as
ever. Pardon us what is paſt, aſſwage the violence of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
Paſſion with one drop of thy moſt precious Blood, and preſerve us from
all Sin for the future. <hi>Deſcende,</hi> look down into our Souls, and
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, how we all endeavour to can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel our Offences by an Act of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
Contrition, being ſorry from the bottom of our Hearts for having ever
diſpleas'd ſo good a God, and this meerly for the Love of thy infinitely
amiable Perſon: And for the ſame Motive we purpoſe to ſuffer whatever
can be ſuffer'd, rather than hereafter to offend thee in the leaſt.
Methinks, Beloved Chriſtians, methinks I am ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that the Bowels of
Divine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are already mov'd towards us; and I doubt not, but every Soul,
that is ſeriouſly converted, feels a Pledge of Almighty God's Mercy, by
perceiving <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56078:14"/>within her ſelf a more perfect Union with him,
who is her Life, and by hearing from him after a peculiar manner, <hi>Anima tua
vivit, Thy Soul lives,</hi> thy Soul is recover'd from her Diſtemper.
<hi>Which Happineſs, through the Interceſſion of the Virgin Mother, God
of his infinite Mercy grant us all.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:56078:15"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books Printed for <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer
to the King's moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty, for his Houſhold and Chappel,
1686. And are to be Sold next door to his Houſe in <hi>Black-fryers,</hi> at
<hi>Richard Cheeſe</hi>'s.</head>
            <p>REflections upon the Anſwer to the <hi>Papiſt
Miſ-repreſented, &amp;c.</hi> Directed to the Anſwerer.
<hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kalendarium Catholicum</hi> for the Year 1686.
<hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Papiſts</hi> Preteſting againſt
<hi>Proteſtant-Popery.</hi> In Anſwer to a Diſcourſe Entituled, <hi>A
Papiſt not Miſ-repreſented by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi> Being a Vindication of
the <hi>Papiſt Miſ-repreſented</hi> and <hi>Repreſented,</hi> and the
<hi>Reflections</hi> upon the Anſwer. <hi>Quart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Copies of Two Papers Written by the late King <hi>Charles</hi> H.
Together with a Paper Written by the late Dutcheſs of <hi>York.</hi>
Publiſh'd by his Majeſty's Command. <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit of Chriſtianity. Publiſh'd by his Majeſty's
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt Sermon Preach'd before their Majeſties in
<hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Windſor,</hi> on the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> of
<hi>October</hi> 1685. By the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father <hi>Dom. Ph. Ellis,</hi> Monk of
the Holy Order of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> and of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Congregation. Publiſh'd by his Majeſty's Command. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Second Sermond Preach'd before the King and Queen, and Queen
Dowager, at their Majeſties Chappel at St. <hi>James's, November</hi> 1.
1685. By the Reverend Father <hi>Dom. Ph. Ellis,</hi> Monk of the Holy Order of
St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> and of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Congregation. Publiſh'd
by his Majeſty's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56078:15"/>
            <p>The Third Sermon Preach'd before the King and Queen, in their
Majeſty's Chappel at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, on the third <hi>Sunday</hi> in
<hi>Advent, December</hi> 13. 1685. By the Reverend Father <hi>Dom. Ph.
Ellis,</hi> Monk of the Holy Order of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> and of the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Congr. Chaplain in Ordinary to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. Publiſh'd
by His Majeſty's Command. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fourth Sermon Preach'd before the King and Queen, in their
Majeſties Chappel at St. <hi>Jame</hi>'s, on <hi>Newyears-day,</hi>
168⅚. By the Reverend Father <hi>Dom. Ph. Ellis,</hi> Monk of the Holy
Order of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> and of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
Chaplain in Ordinary to his Majeſty. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixth Sermon Preach'd before the King and Queen, in their
Majeſties Chappel at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, upon the firſt
<hi>Wedneſday</hi> in <hi>Lent,</hi> Febr. 24. 1685. By the Reverend Father
<hi>Dom. Ph. Ellis,</hi> Monk of the Holy Order of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> and
of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Congregation. Publiſh'd by his Majeſties
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Catholic Church in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of Controverſie. By the Right Reverend <hi>James Benigne Boſſiset,</hi>
Counſellor to the King, Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> formerly of
<hi>Condom,</hi> and Preceptor to the <hi>Dauphin:</hi> Firſt Almoner to the
<hi>Dauphineſs.</hi> Done into <hi>Engliſh</hi> with all the former
Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations, and others newly Publiſh'd in the Ninth and Laſt Editions of
the <hi>French.</hi> Publiſh'd by his Majeſty's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.
<hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd before the King and Queen, in Their Majeſties
Chappel at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, upon the <hi>Annunciation</hi> of our
Bleſſed Lady, <hi>March</hi> 25. 1686. By <hi>Jo. Betham</hi> Doctor of
<hi>Sorbon.</hi> Publiſh'd by his Majeſty's Command. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Abſtract of the <hi>Douay Catechiſm,</hi> for the Uſe of
Children and Ignorant People. Now Revis'd, and much Amended. Publiſh'd with
Allowance. <hi>Twentyfours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Paſtoral Letter from the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> to
the <hi>New Catholics</hi> of his Dioceſs, Exhorting them to keep their
<hi>Eaſter,</hi> and giving them Neceſſary Advertiſements-againſt the
<hi>Falſe Paſtoral Letters</hi> of their <hi>Miniſters.</hi> With
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the <hi>Pretended Perſecution.</hi> Publiſh'd with
Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56078:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Anſwer of the <hi>New Converts</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> to a
<hi>Paſtoral Letter</hi> from a <hi>Proteſtant Miniſter.</hi> Done out of
<hi>French,</hi> and Publiſh'd with Allowance. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ceremonies for Healing of them that be Diſeaſed with the
Kings Evil, uſed in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> VII. Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by His
Majeſties Command. <hi>Quarto</hi> in Latin, <hi>Twelves</hi> in
Engliſh.</p>
            <p>A Short Chriſtian Doctrine. Compoſed by the R. Father
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bellarmin,</hi> of the Society of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and Cardinal
Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Allowance. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Vindication of the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Expoſition of
the Doctrine of the Catholic Church. In Anſwer to a Book Entituled, <hi>An
Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
With a Letter from the ſaid Biſhop. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſis Superiorum.
Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
